discussed price goes to the less liquid side because market orders need limit orders as
transactory right yeah so if there's much much much thicker and i'll give you you know numerical examples again
if there was one thousand dollars worth of sell limit orders and ten dollars worth of buy limit orders
you could buy 999 dollars worth and price would move nowhere at that price level there
if you sold 11 which is significantly less than the amount being brought the exact same time
price would go down right so this is much much less liquid specifically it's only 1% of the liquidity
compared to the sell liquidity
and it requires much less selling
to push price in that direction.
So if you can identify
this particular
particularly skewed environment
where there's less liquidity
on any side of the market
compared to the other
and you trade in that direction,
you'll make money.
Price will consistently go that
in that direction.
Yeah.
It doesn't matter if there is a big buyer there.
It does not matter.
statistically price will go down. So this has kind of been providing an answer, well, this
should be providing an answer to this question of where is the edge? We're using price to predict
future movements. If you think about what causes price to go up or down, it's obviously more
market orders compared to the available limit orders. Now, in this instance, forget price
going to say, let's take aside for a minute. There was 10 bi-limit orders there, or $10 worth
combine in the orders.
I decide to go short.
So this is what happens.
In my mind,
I receive the information
or I come to the conclusion
I want to go short.
That's new information.
That isn't being reflected in the market
because it's still in my mind.
I click the button.
The trade goes to the trade server
on my platform server.
From the platform server,
it goes to my broker.
Then from the broker, either he fills it
or he hedges it out into the market.
He goes to,
to the prime broker. The prime broker then goes to the real market, fills it, and then it
comes all the way back. And now, as it was filling the order, price went down in this instance,
yeah? Price goes down. Yeah. So the trade has all, this trade information is now historical
information. It has nothing to do with the future. Every single piece of ticking, price movement,
every single piece of candlesticks, candles that you see in charts historically are all,
information. So how can we be using old information to predict future price movements? Again,
that's another reason why this idea of conventional technical analysis, basic price action,
people taking a very overly simplistic approach. There's not edge in what you are doing. You're trying
to use historical data to predict future price movements. What I say is there's conditions where
because of the behaviors of liquidity providers and how they deal with volume, they can create a
condition because of some of their behaviors when they're trying to avoid taking on short
positions there's too big of buyer here yeah there's large buy volume they don't want to take on
short positions because if they go short here price is likely to move against them and they have
losing cell positions so they remove their cell liquidity and that sucks price higher and higher and
that particular behavior is creating a condition which has a lag effect or it has a sequence of
events that take place after them. So volume shot comes in. That's larger than the
equity provider wants to take on. The liquidity provider starts to pull that volume higher
looking for liquidity in his own book, right? That is stretching the volume out,
making it trade thinly at each price level. It's trying to find liquidity. So there's
100 million being brought. It's split into small pieces. The liquidity provider pulls its
price higher that is buy volumes trying to put it to trade at.
The liquidity providers pulling the ass price deeper into his own book, trying to find sell
liquidity. Essentially, he's splitting this $100 million and filling in small pieces wherever
there's sell liquidity in the book. So it's trading very, very thinly. Now, whilst this is
happening, other liquidity providers are having to keep the prices the same, they then also
queue up any volume that's waiting behind. So there's $100 million. They have some other buy
volume come in. They have to formalize it into a queue. The same way,
this is being put into a queue, there's 100 million there, 10 gets filled there, there's
90 million left the queue, then the other 90 million has to go to the next price level
wherever they sell liquidity to find it. It's counterpoint. There's 80 million left in the queue,
right? So the queue and the volume up, trying to find liquidity for it in-house,
whilst the other liquidity providers, they also remove liquidity, they have to keep prices
the same, they can't offer the amount of liquidity that may or may not actually be in the buck
out to the market.
So at this price level, let's say
is price two.
The second dealer at price two
had 470 million on sell liquidity.
He couldn't offer it out to the market
because if he did,
dealer one moves prices against it,
continues to move prices higher
and now there's been a breakdown in prices.
Somebody's going to arbitrage against them.
Okay, so within these environments,
the real supply of liquidity
is not being passed on to the market.
These guys are actually controlling the supply,
removing sell liquidity, resulting in a super, super thinly traded price movement.
So price ends up traveling higher.
It travels further than it should.
There's greater volatility inside of it.
And with inside of it, it traded very thin.
There wasn't huge transactions that were matched with the buyers and sellers.
Yeah.
Okay.
Now, the after effect of that is inside of this whole area, there's thin by liquidity left behind.
there is no real buyer there.
The only reason price went up that fast
is because the sell liquidity
was running away from it.
No willing buyer is willing to accept
at these higher and higher prices.
No willing buyer comes and says,
okay, we're now going to position here
and build up a huge position here.
The real buy liquidity stays down there
at the origin of the move.
So when this price run eventually exhausts,
you have a new condition that's created
where there's weak bi-liquidity
and relatively thick-a-sell liquidity.
If you trade it on this condition
and you short it at that thin point,
the further the price travels higher,
it gets thinner and thin-not.
So by that what I mean is,
the hundred million,
the further it goes higher,
it gets filled, filled, filled, filled, filled,
until there's hardly anything fucking enough behind.
There's only one million left to get filled.
Are you following me?
Yeah, yeah, yeah.
So you eventually reach a stage
at the exhaustion point
where there's much, this significantly nested by liquidity,
it doesn't even take that much sell liquidity to absorb the remaining volume
and any like sell volume that comes in any market orders that come in
will quite easily push price down yeah so here it's not historical information
anymore this new price event that's taking place that is that you know the price
room that super super thin is drawing higher trying to find sell liquidity which is running away
is creating a new condition i.e. is leaving behind the weak liquidity
when it's left behind weak liquidity
and the buying finally dries off
there's nothing there to hold it up
the real buy liquidity is down here
yeah
so any light cell volume
is able to push price back down
so this condition
it results in a sequence of events
my sequence I mean one
two three four
things happen in order
you have the volume shot
the buy volume
that results in the liquidity provider
with drawing liquidity
so the ask price the sell liquidity runs away is removed the buy volume chases price is higher
resulting in a really really thinly traded move which has nothing left inside of it or hardly
any bi liquidity left inside of it and then at the end point the exhaustion point you have
weak bi liquidity thicker sell liquidity any light volume is able to push price down so after
four we're seeing the exhaustion fill now if I asked you based on what the information I've just
told you you have this thin move which is being stretched out and the buy volume dries off what does
that mean when i say the buy volume dries off there's no more willing buyers in the market well
no because willing buyers let's just say i had a hundred million order here price went up i wanted
this hundred million to get filled very quickly so i placed buy limit orders there there is willing
buyers there by liquidity could be considered as willing buyers it's hit it's hit a
a thicker sell liquidity then?
No, no.
By volume, I mean
market orders. So when
buy volume dries off, I'm talking
about the aggressive,
time sensitive, driving
market orders that cause price
to push out. Because
let's settle, you know, let's settle
some confusion here anyway.
If there's this range at this low,
it can sustain forever.
Forever and ever and ever.
That range does not have to go
anywhere if there's no market
orders pushing it out. So there
could be 100 million
buy liquidity there and 100 million
sell liquidity there.
What is liquidity?
Limits orders.
Limit orders. Okay.
Now let's just say for the next
three, four minutes,
buying happens. So they buy 10,
the buy 10, the buy 10, the buy 10,
until there's only 10 million
sell liquidity left. Right?
Yeah. The buy liquidity
is still relatively thick
nobody's sold into it
nobody's picked it out
under this condition
if a market order buy
comes through
that is simply
I don't know
30 million
it's not a huge amount
there's much
there's much greater
by liquidity
than a much greater
buy volume
market order volume
than the available
to sell liquidity
right
the liquidity
provider in this instance
will be very unlikely
to try to go short
10 million
sorry to try to go short
against this 30 million
here. In other words, they don't want
to fill it. Yeah.
Right? Instead,
they pull the ask price higher because
there might be, at this price, there might be
7 million, there might be 10 million there,
there might be
17 million here.
So the liquidity provider is looking on his own
inside of his own order book and seeing that
there's a thicker area of sell liquidity here,
he then needs to take this 30 million and pull it
higher and match it off.
You get it?
because he doesn't want to take on the short
30 million risk. If the dealer
goes short here, he's gone
short 30 million. He has a sell position.
There's only 10 million
above price that he can buy back.
So he gets out
10 million. He has 20 million left to buy back.
What's the next position he can buy
back at? Or back up there.
So the risk
of price going against him
is extremely high if he took on a
short position here. The reason
is extremely high is because this thin,
sell liquidity in the first place.
Yeah, there is.
You get it.
So, so, um, when you refer to, um, volume, you're on about market orders.
Always.
Always market orders.
Okay.
Always.
So this is 30 million volume.
Yeah.
It pushes higher.
The liquidity provider withdraws this ask price.
He's then trying to find this, they sell orders in the book and match this 30 million worth.
So the first price, 10 million.
He's matched 20 left there.
Go to the next.
price seven matched 30 left over 10 match there three left over 17 left there the matches three
14 million left over here right by volume is now dead up it's finished 30 million's been
matched yeah now within this specific example how much was traded here in this region so there was
20 then 13 and 36 no no but how much was traded here
oh nothing
absolutely nothing
yeah
so price
could have easily
moved
10%
from here to here
making it seem
like a very big move
but in reality
there was hardly
anything traded here
okay
yeah
why did price
then jump 10%
it had to match
the
the orders
because that that's
the
purpose of market
there was very
there was very thin
sell liquidity
that's why I was jumping
the sell liquidity
sufficient to fill the 30 million
was spread out over 10% worth of prices
there's 10 million plus 7 that's 17 plus 10 that's
27 the final 3 that's required is
is there yeah that 30 million was
spread out over a big distance a 10% distance
of prices so that's why when a volume came in
it wasn't a big shot of volume it was still able to push
price up 10% because the volume had to find liquidity
price went to the less liquid side the less liquid side this example is extremely extremely illiquid
yeah by illiquid i mean this 30 million couldn't find his counterparties without moving price 10
that's very illiquid all right now in this instance there's hardly anything traded here
the hundred million buyers remember is that volume or is that liquidity no that's liquidity that's
there. Okay, so prices now
jumped up 10%. That's
100 million buyers down here.
Realistically,
if these 100 million buyers was,
let's just say that's me, if I had a high,
high urgency to get filled,
I want to get filled as soon as possible,
I might take these 100 million orders
and stack them here.
So now there's 100 million holding price up.
So when the market order buy volume dries off,
it does leave behind
an area where there's no buy liquidity.
there, right?
Why is that?
So you're referring to
how it leaves nothing there?
Yeah.
Where is the buy liquidity?
It's lower than that.
Here.
Yeah.
So here there's no buy liquidity, yeah?
The market order buying is dried off,
so it's not driving prices
to find sell limit orders anymore.
Sell limit orders have absorbed
three million less, the last bit of buyers.
Yeah.
So now we have a condition
with this 14 million
sell limit orders here
all the way down to there
is zero by limit orders
yeah so it has to go to that
that price 100 million
well any order that comes down
it's going to push price right down to there
immediately almost instantaneously
it'll go smack down right down to there
to find equity you get it
so now just imagine that instance
where those buyers didn't turn up there
that 100 million buyer
he's not willing to accept
that high those higher prices there
price only moved out there
because the sell
the liquidity provider
was trying to deal inside of his own book
pulling prices higher
imagine there's a completely separate book here
right this is your dealer
that dealer within these same prices
had 50 million
selling an order there
then in reality this 30 million
should have gone to here
which is the same price
found the counterpart
party and then whatever happens
price shouldn't have broke out to a new
basically price shouldn't have broken out to this
are you following me
yeah yeah if that sell liquidity
which is on another
dealer's book was given to this volume
on the first dealer's book
yeah price wouldn't have a stretch so far
okay
now that's an example of the inefficiency of the market
where the fragmentation of it
i.e. there's liquidity there, there's liquidity there.
They spread across two different venues.
If it was all under one single venue, the market would not have broke out that fast.
Yeah. Okay. So the point I'm really making here is the real market value, the real desire to trade is really still within this range.
Yeah. Yeah. Even though one dealer caused price to push out this much because he wanted to keep information in-house and match it off in-house, this move out is as simple then dislover.
location. It's just a spike away from the true area of value.
Yeah.
And as long as this 100 million wants to continue trading down here.
And remember, this is just me in this example.
What if there was the majority of this asset traders, the bi-liquity, the majority of it maintained
itself down there, i.e. it remained back down at this core area.
Then this whole move out, it leaves behind a lack of liquidity.
It will never be completely illiquid, all right?
It will never be that is absolutely zero there,
but it will be significantly less buy liquidity at these areas
than the real core liquidity down there.
So any light selling is able to push price down.
Here, where the market order buying dried off, the driving force,
when that market order buying dried off,
you had thicker sell liquidity than the market order buyers
and much thinner by liquidity left behind.
So that's an example.
of there being a skewed book.
Okay.
All right?
So here I'm just kind of explaining
under which condition there's edge structurally
how the behaviours of other market participants
allow us to consistently predict future price movements
with not trading something random anymore.
It is definitely random when this move will break out.
Nobody can tell you that.
Nobody can tell you what some Japanese trader
decides to push a button at the right time
that can trigger the protective mechanism
that liquidity providers employ.
But what you can say is because of those actions
and because of this protective mechanism,
when this environment is underway,
it's creating a condition which in the future
is basically unsustainable.
This move cannot sustain itself.
It's creating too much weakness.
Once the volume dries off,
there's always going to be a weaker side.
There's always going to be thinned by liquidity left behind.
So there's absolutely,
some edge when you're trading this condition
when you're trying to trade
the effect of these market participants
which is creating market inefficiencies
yeah
all right so again it's critical you understand
why this edge here what we're doing here
why we're focusing on this particular behavior
and within this behavior we're going to break
this this structure down from the origin
to the move up to the exhaustion
point to the reversal and back down we broke those structures into categories or we categorize
them we break them into stages so we can identify where along this series of price events we are
so the first price event obviously is the volume short yeah second volume of second event is
price obviously runs third event is exhaustion fourth event is the shift and the fifth event is the
exhaust is the is the is the fill basically now each of these are different stages at any given
point when you open up a chart price could be alongside any of these or within any of these stages
so we need to be able to accurately identify where along this this stage we are or this
sequence we are that's why each of these one each of these numbers will have very very specific
characteristics that different from each other and we're going to start to look into them
but here what I've done is I've slightly simplified it
because again last session we discussed
one dealer can deal inside of his own book
and the other dealer can have
there's a fish hole
there's buying going on
buyers need sell market order buying going on
they need sell equity
the sell liquidity is stretched out here
the size of the red line
signifies the amount of liquidity
the distance between them
signifies how far stretched out it is
within this dealer too's book
who might have a sell limit order there
is it the dealer's sell limit order
no it's the
it's not the dealers
it's the people who actually
yeah it could be a client
it could be a corporate client
that wants to do business at that price
for whatever reason
who's placed a sell limit order
with his dealer there
these dealers have quite a rich network
of internal liquidity
they've built their own liquidity pools
over time by keeping clients
trade with them
so when a client does go long
market order long at the right time
it's reasonable for them
to just try to fill it in-house
so in this example
that I gave you a minute ago
with price moved 10%
it's very unlikely
right
they'd be able to fill a 10 million order
in-house probably within one pip
two pips
however
the amount of sell equity here
isn't always the same
and what can happen is
this original 10 million shot
from the client won at dealer one
they start moving prices higher
trying to fill the 10 million
that then results in
follow through buying from other dealers
and they all go into this protective state
of not wanting to provide sell liquidity
even if there was
20 billion worth of sell liquidity
collectively at the other two dealers
at the other three dealers
at this price
they are not supplying that liquidity out to the market
all of them go into protective state
well even if they've got 20 billion
yeah because it's split up
this guy's moving prices higher
everybody
then is sorry
this guy's moving prices higher
i.e. the dealer does not want to take short positions
they have to keep prices the same
so by the time
the dealer
this original dealer's gone from this price
to this price
if these guys are still down here
offering 20 billion worth of sell liquidity
you could buy here
sell to this guy immediately
yeah why
because then you
what's the word
you're taking advantage of
the market
you make a profit of that
they can't allow that
yeah but why can you take advantage of that
because of prime brokerage
there's going to be prime brokerage clients that can see this guy's
price you can see this guy's price
as soon as those prices break away
there's going to be someone there to try to exploit that
the algorithms
the really fast ones
it could be a HFT system
Yeah, typically it'll be a HFT client, but they can exploit those price breakdowns.
So it doesn't matter how much liquidity is at this price level.
If dealers are pushing their, if one dealer starts to push their prices higher,
it triggers a response from all the others where they have to keep prices the same.
So if price goes from one to two here, these guys also have to go to one to two.
Then it goes from two to three.
These guys also have to go two to three.
now at this price this dealer at price three has no sell liquidity there so he quickly has to go to
price four to fill this 10 million right okay yeah why is he why does he have to go inside of
why is you trying to find 10 million here or why is you trying to fill the 10 million here
I'm not filling the 10 million there because he's doing it in-house exactly so he's filling
the quotes in house and he's got liquidity at different places he's moved from 3 to 4 but
these guys are now triggering
across these three price levels
across these three dealers, sorry,
the equivalent of 20 billion worth of sell limits.
They have to buy them themselves.
Okay.
Because if they, if,
imagine 20 million of sell liquidity
came out on offer to all these buyers here.
They're now going long at this price.
No?
They all go along at price three.
When dealer number four
has already gone to price four.
they can immediately sell to that motherfucker.
Yeah, that's true.
Prices are broke down.
These guys have sold liquidity too cheap.
And this guy's brought volume high to it.
He's brought too high.
So now there's been a breakdown.
So the point of making is there can be a lot of liquidity available at this price level three.
But because one dealer started to price inside price liquidity in-house,
that can cause these other guys to not provide that $20 billion out to the market.
They avoid taking on short positions, number one.
Number two, they're controlling the supply of sell equity,
which is resulting in these buyers now,
having to accept higher and higher prices to find sell equity amongst receiving,
but from the receiving dealer flow and the corresponding or responding dealers.
So by the one, I mean, is Bank five starts moving its prices high.
We know that's all good.
bank four also then copies dealer what dealifies prices so when dealer five goes from one to two bank four goes from one to two
bank five goes from two to three finds no sell liquidity at three whilst bank four at three has some sell liquidity
let's say 40 million bank five quickly jumps from three to four bank four has to keep in line so he also
jumps from three to four and he himself has to go long at 40 million so bank four
has now gone longer 40 million.
Back five moves prices from four to five.
Bank four moves from price four to five.
Now, let's just say bank four hits some of the client's stop losses because they were just
there.
That's what happens.
That results in buy is coming through.
So now $20 million worth of buy market orders coming through.
Bank five moves from five to six.
Bank four also moves from five to six.
But now he has $40 million to sell to those stop losses.
yeah right so he's basically raised inventory
as prices traveling higher by taking the opposite side of clients
and then they're able to distribute that inventory
in pieces behind the given ask price so the ask price is moving higher and higher
amongst all these banks and they're able to distribute liquidity behind the ask
price time and time again okay all right so the control of the supply of liquidity
now one final point I was talking about a scenario where bank five
led to initial buy-in and then bank four hit stop losses bank three also led to more buying
more buying more buy-in now there's a whole wave of extra buying going on all these banks essentially
will turn into um will essentially start to pull their ass prices higher to avoid getting clipped
by that what i mean is they don't want these these buyers to be able to clip the ask price so now this
dealer turns massively short yeah right they'll control the supply and the amount of sell equity
they'll try to raise inventory by going long against limit orders
and simultaneously the key prices the same.
The effect is, of course, price runs further than it should.
One dealer can initiate the response
or the other dealers can respond.
The behaviours of the other dealers are basically avoiding providers sell liquidity,
even if there's real sell liquidity there,
that causes price to run higher and higher and higher,
and we have this eventual price run.
That's the point.
What I want you to do is go through obviously these,
like you should
basically know this inside out
yeah
here's an example
of price being relatively stable
shooting out
and drawing back in
on really really light selling
is drawing back in
and then it shoots out again
it comes really very very thin
let's just say
it was 20 million long
it was filled two
three six
until there's hardly anything left behind
or in terms of volume
and at that exhaustion point
it was traded thinly up
the real bi-liquity is down there and price draws back down towards the origin right yeah um
this origin pop out draw back to origin this origin pop out draw back to origin is essentially this
okay but it can happen on any time frame can't it it can happen on any time frame it could be
five pips it could be 60 pips it could be six thousand pips so if i look at a few examples of that on cable
we have one on the daily chart or we have not just one but
so probably probably be good to go for the higher time frame ones then might have more
liquidity not necessarily they're not going to happen that frequently
if you want to be if you want to be an active day trader
you had one trade there and you ride it higher for like you know
so we we definitely use higher time frame but no
we'll there's so much information that we need after one minutes
of the tick charts
for time in a trade
for selecting a trade
for avoiding a trade
to assess if these levels
are strong
et cetera
we need to use
timeframes as a zoom in tool
literally as a fucking microscope
you sometimes
these are larger view
sometimes you need to zoom in
to inspect inside of things
timing of trade
you get the tightest trades
based off the one minute
even if I'm trading
a higher time frame context
but the whole point
before we get into that kind of
of is that doesn't matter if price is going up, it exhausts, it dries off and it has to come
back down to find buy liquidity. The only reason, the only reason price went from here and popped
out this inefficiently is because when that buy volume came through, the market order buy,
the sell equity disappeared and drew away.
Causing price to chase after it and stretch out, causing the volume to chase after and stretch
out, leave it behind that thinly traded move. Whilst the real buy liquidity,
remain down there.
Okay.
So price dislocates, it breaks away from the real buy liquidity, the real desire to trade.
As a result of dealer's removing liquidity, creates that inefficiency, that distortion.
And at that stage, you have weak bids, thicker sell liquidity, it takes light selling
the push price down, and that's exactly what happens.
So even though price ends up from here to here, it doesn't go in a straight line.
it actually pops out, becomes really, really, really, un-sustainable, really, really inefficient,
dries often comes back here.
Does it again.
And again, and again.
Now, at the end of that, this whole move itself also is relatively thin.
It's not exactly that inefficient.
So the point in making is that whole move was composed of sideways, pops, draw back in,
sideways pops draw back in
those smaller structures
made the overall price swing
relatively thinly traded as well
by that way
if we look at what I mean
this area thinly traded
this area thinly traded but it was
the price kind of sorted it out
and came back to find by liquidity
this area thinly traded
so within this whole price move
we have pretty significant areas
inside of it that haven't really got
that much buy liquidity in those areas.
All right, it's leaving weaknesses behind.
So once the buying dries off, so let's just say there was 100 million, filled it,
filled it, filled it, reloaded again, filled some, reloaded again, filled some.
Now the 100 million and the subsequent buying has dried off, where's the buy liquidity
that's holding price up?
Well, you have areas and massive areas of weakness there.
You may have some residual buy liquidity in these pockets, but typically it won't be that
much until we get down to
the origins.
Okay.
All right, so we'll be
defining how and why
this is inefficient
and this is inefficient
but of course this is
this has greater
inefficiency. It has much, much
less buy liquidity left behind compared
to this one.
But both are still thinly traded.
There was still buying going on here
and not enough of their liquidity. It was still
creating pockets of weakness
and areas of thinly traded
prices
leaving behind those weaknesses
this just left more
thinly traded prices behind
What about to the left of that
there, the move down?
It was inefficient as well
Okay
Yep
This whole move down is inefficient
It's relatively inefficient
But still, this is the most inefficient
area of price
That you can see on this whole job
Actually, no, that would be
But they already filled it
So at each of these instances, you would have had a volume shot, push price higher,
the sell liquidity draw away, or in this instance, you had a market order sell,
the bi-liquity ran away, price chases after, or the cell volume chases after it,
stretches out, stretches out, stretches out until here it's at its thinnest.
The cell volume's dried off, it's left behind weak-cell liquidity,
and it's hitting some by-liquity.
That is the perfect condition.
for a market order to come in
and immediately push price back up.
Okay.
So it's at these exhaustion points
where you have the highest probability
of a move in one direction over a number.
So price can go up and go down.
There's two possible outcomes.
Here, the probability of price going up
is greatly, greatly skewed
compared to it going down.
Why?
Well, look at the move.
it's done
but why though
why is it likely to go up
compared down it's not a trick question it's easy
market orders are coming
no
you cannot predict why a market order
will come through why is it likely
to go up then down
there's weakness on one side of the market
exactly there's then
sell liquidity there right
now these are the behaviours that occur
in markets there's a matter the direction
there's a matter where prices are going
on the way to a direction the volume
isn't buying, buying, buying, buying, buying, buying,
forever, it's actually, you have, it comes in in cycles and it comes in in series.
So you have bidding going on. That bidding at that point dries off.
Price has to draw down to find more by liquidity.
Price stabilizes. Then the volume shot can come in again.
And then it dries off. Price comes down, finds by liquidity, stabilizes, there's nothing.
Then the volume shot comes in again. And it's a constant repetition.
in uptrends of buying, but never consistent.
Sorry, never constant.
It's consistently getting bid up, but not constantly getting bid up.
That creates, of course, again, a unique dynamic
where we can rely on price to draw out,
become super, super inefficient and come back into range,
rather than continue to trend out of range like that.
So is it not constant because volume isn't constant?
Exactly.
we're going to look at the way which large orders are filled they could quite easily have been a 50 million order long position probably more than that but it could quite easily have been like a 500 million long order being filled from here to here but that 500 million order isn't a buy market order buy that's doing buy buy buy buy buy buy it actually trades in a different way all right we'll have a look at that at the necessary stage because I think if I discuss that today it will be a bit confusing
it's really transacted through
limit orders basically
it's not going to be market order buyers
market order buys are still coming through
from other clients
but there could be a very very thick
and large buy order that's trying to get filled
that's having to hide this information
so they're split into small limit orders
and as the price run travels higher
it'll continue to place those orders
an X percentage away from the bid and ask
but again
again it's just way way
way too difficult for you at this stage.
What I'm explaining is you can have an area of stability where there's weak sell liquidity
here and relatively thicker by liquidity here because it's picking it up from there.
When a market order buy comes through, it's easy to push price out because there's less
sell liquidity there.
That original weakness coupled with a market order buy triggers one liquidity provider to start
fitting that trade and that then causes a response from everybody else or the other liquidity
providers right so sell liquidity that would have been there is not given out to the market order
it draws away the market order chases after it chases after it chases after it chases after it
until the market order buying dries off finally hits the area of sell liquidity and then whatever's
left behind is quite thinly traded price subsequently draws down now in this instance as you can
imagine some, the buy liquidity actually went here and then it supported prices. The same thing
happened. Price stabilized. Volume shot, price dried off, came back down. Buy liquidity excepting
higher prices. Stabilized, volume shot, price ran out. Came back down. This time there was no
by liquidity and it was able to continue selling. But the behaviors are consistently the same.
Price becomes super, super, super, super thin, dries off, draws back in. Price becomes super, super super
thin here, dries off, draws back in. Price becomes super, super, super thin here, dries off, draws back in.
Price becomes super, super thin, dries off, draws back in. Here it becomes very, very, very inefficient,
dries off, draws back in within the next minute. Here, it becomes very, very inefficient,
draws back in. Here, it's quite stable, pops out. As you can imagine, there's a volume shot,
market order buy, sell equity disappearing, it chases after it, chases after it, chases after it,
chases after it, market order dries off,
leaving behind that weakness, it comes right back into the last
dealing wage.
Pops out, draws back in.
Pops out, majorly, draws back in.
Pops out majorly, draws back in.
Pops out, draws back in.
Doesn't matter where we look at it, what it is.
In FX, you continue to see buyers,
turn up because they're great demand for buy liquidity. And you see sellers consistently turn up
because, again, I have a great demand for some liquidity. Bires and sellers demand liquidity
on both sides of the market because the diversity of the types of clients is, you know,
there's a high level of our diversity. You have corporate clients. You have real money transatlantic
clients. You have leveraged clients like hedge funds. You have governments, central banks.
It's a broad, broad array of different types of clients demanding liquidity, resulting in buyers,
and sell liquidity on both sides of the market
rather than compared to a market
where sellers sell, sellers sell forever and ever and ever
or buys buy, buyers buy forever and ever and ever.
In a market where buyers buy with each other,
like let's say Dow Jones Industrial,
you have a significant buy liquidity hold price up
that accepts higher prices,
but relatively thin sell liquidity.
What do you think that results in?
Thicker buy thin sell.
price just moving further up?
Yeah, very, very consistently.
So if you look at this on a larger scale,
that's all that these larger assets do.
Sorry, these risk assets do.
Or these indexes composed of risk assets.
So the Dow Jones industry has made upon
the 30 largest highly capitalized companies
in the whole of America,
companies like IBM, Coca-Cola,
they are the biggest companies in the world
in terms of marginalization.
This takes the prices of their
shares and basically adds them all up, basically.
There's obviously weightings to them, but the value of this index consistently trends up
for a very, very, very long period of time.
This is only till 24-E, and if you looked at the real chart from 19-pocket 70s, it's just
an uptrend, right?
Because what happens consistently is buy liquidity accepts higher and higher prices.
you can just imagine
it is absolutely impossible
for Price to have
held up here
if there wasn't by liquidity
providing support
it's absolutely impossible
it's absolutely impossible for Price
to continue drifting through this whole area
up up up up
if there was not
weak sell liquidity in the way
if there was sell liquidity
that was very very thick
price would not have pushed past it
now obviously there's times like these where events happen but they're just event driven about this is not the natural environment this is a fucking black swan type not necessarily black swan events but the events you know the kind of implication of an event is it's unforeseen you don't expect it to happen is something new is something significant that's typically what you could classify as an event in the context of markets at least yeah that move very thin down second
that second time, most recent time.
Yeah, look, this is a weekly chart.
So this, if you looked at this on a 30-year chart, it's nothing.
It's absolutely fucking nothing.
But the point I'm really trying to raise here is,
FX markets, they don't do this.
You have sell liquidity here, you have buy liquidity here,
and price will maintain a range.
It might trend, but it trends in a very, very large range, basically.
You have a big range here, then it ranges here.
for fucking 20 years
and then it ranges here for 20 years, you get it
because there's buy liquidity and sell liquidity
for different reasons, not speculative reasons
whereas in Dow Jones Industrial Average
most of the people buying this
are going to be their own companies buying their own shares
back and or global investors
taking on risk.
Okay, yeah, that's why it's moving
like that.
Yes, you have one-sided liquidity
basically, one-sided liquidity,
buy liquidity. There's definitely
sell liquidity in the market, but the third
the thicker, larger, much, much more consistent side is obviously the buy side.
Now, you go over to an asset like the pound over the last five years.
All it's done really is range, range, range within a trend.
It's only trended for a number of weeks.
Again, massive ranges, massive, massive ranges.
This whole area is basically a range.
And then it trends for a couple of weeks.
And then you have massive ranges again.
And again, sometimes it trends for a couple of weeks.
because like I said
the stability
sorry the characteristics of the FX market
and who supplies liquidity both sides of the market
demand liquidity for various different reasons
even within trends
there's no real
driven environments really is more stable
70% of the time the FX market stable
resulting in quite a high level of reliability
for me to expect buyers to turn up in these levels
and sell it to turn up in these levels quite consistently.
Now, what that basically means is,
if there is a series of buying or a period of buying going on,
there's still going to be cell liquidity that turns up.
And with the result of buy volume drying off consistently as well,
so there's a buyer here.
He wants to buy 100 million.
There's sell liquidity here.
There's only 10 million cell liquidity.
When the market order comes through,
it results and triggers that.
price chasing mechanism price draws out but the hundred million stays down there yeah okay when that
market order buying dries off eventually dries off it the move up create to that area of weakness
price subsequently dries off draws back down to find the buyers and then takes on its next move all right
so the point i'm really making here is each of these price runs they they have a level of
inventory pushing along with them.
There might be an inventory of $50 billion
pushing it along with this price run here.
So if we just look at that price run,
okay, so what we consistently saw here is
buyers dry off, market order buyers dry off.
Proceeding that price was really, really, really thin.
And then once these legs dried off,
price eventually subsequently fills back to like the last area,
you could argue.
Right?
so price dries off, sorry, it becomes super, super thin, dries off, draws back down to the last area.
Here, shoots out again, becomes super, super thin, draws back down to the last area.
Here you have an area of stability, price shoots out, becomes super, super thin, draws back down to the last area.
Now, the point I'm making is that there is a large, large buyer holding price up here, a very, very large buyer.
It could be one firm.
It could be a single hedge fund taking on the view that the pound is undervalued and it is a speculative position or it could be a large, large corporation who's invested heavy amounts in the UK who is now trying to get out of the UK, right?
He's trying to limit their exposure to the UK.
Sorry, that's pound going up.
So it might be because a large investor is taking a bet that the UK economy is supposed to do well.
They want to, I don't know, they want to invest in the construction sector.
So they need to exchange a huge amount of dollars into the pound, so they're buying the pound.
Now, it's quite unrealistic for them to turn around and try to buy, I don't know, $100 billion in one day without price going, but without the costs of buying that $100 billion, they come in very, very high.
So this is exactly what happens.
If you want to trade large in the market, you have liquidity issues.
You can't just buy $100 billion at the ask price and get filled.
That's the thinnest point in equity, the bidding and ask.
You have to hide your information.
Now there's two ways you can.
Well, there's a number of ways you can get filled, yeah?
You can go market order long, $100 billion and send the market into a fucking,
it depends on what platform you fill it with.
You could fill it on a multi-dealer platform.
You might get a few hundred million quite quickly within about seven pips.
But after that, you're going to start to get slipped.
You're going to start to get re-quoted.
You will not get nice fields.
Realistically, no platform in the world would allow you to go $100 billion long in one order.
You'd have to break into pieces yourself anyway.
Okay.
All right.
Now, you could go to your bank directly and on the electronic trading platform, try to go $100 billion long again.
Again, the platform will split your order into small pieces and it will result in the dealer internalizing all your flow.
you'll get really, really shit, shit execution.
It'll take the whole day to fill your trade
because they're dealing in house
and you'll, again, get massively slipped.
Why?
You try to buy $100 billion,
all that information leaked in one single trade
and your dealer knew to avoid taking short against you.
So you have to hide it from your dealer.
The other option is you go along with a limit order.
So you place the limit order here at this price level.
What is the likelihood of price coming into your,
level and having a hundred billion worth of market order selling going on at that time.
Not very.
Depending on where your order is as well.
Your order is likely going to be on a single-dealer platform with the dealer.
It might be on a multi-dealer platform.
There's a higher likelihood you'll be able to access greater liquidity.
But it's very unlikely that price comes into your level fills you for a total of $100 billion before, you know, it's very unlikely that'll happen without it moving away.
so you might get price might come down there might be 50 million worth of selling left over so yeah you know you get filled you have 950 billion left over you got filled your long 50 million and maybe now people are consistently seeing that every time this level gets hit there's unlimited liquidity it seems like the first time it seemed like that 50 million couldn't push price down another 50 million comes through it can't push another 50 million comes through it can't push by this point these sellers
They quickly realize that there's a large, large buyer here, absorbing any selling.
So you've now only been filled for 150 million.
You have a very, very big amount left over, 8.50 million.
And before that, everybody else clocks on, the sellers withdraw.
Any light market order that comes through is pushing price up,
away from where you want to transact.
In other words, what I'm saying is your $100 million is too large to get filled at a single price.
Okay.
So you can't limit order it.
You can't market order it.
however for these type of large trades basically brokers what I mean by that is liquidity providers
have given their clients a suite of algorithm options execution algorithms that'll fill the trade for
them so it's literally like a ticket like this in the ticket you put in you want to buy a hundred
billion you put in that you want it filled within 50 pips so what that means is the max slippage
you're allowing is 50 pips.
Also, you put in the time of day you wanted to start filling the trade.
It could be in the morning, it could be at night, it could be middle of the day.
You can say that you wanted to fill every day from 8 a.m. to 10 a.m. for the next week.
So you can instruct, there's a time element as well. And also, you get to choose whether it's
aggressive, passive, or medium risk. So aggressive would suggest that you want the order
filled as quickly as possible.
Medium suggests that you want the order filled
but with the least
volatility possible
and passive means that you're okay
with waiting for price to come to your level.
So let's just say
the bid and ask is here at that time.
That's where the bid is, that's where the ask prices.
If your algorithm is on aggressive,
you want your order to get filled
as quickly as possible.
what that means is you will accept
basically this algorithm on aggressive
will start to place your 100 million in small pieces here
at the higher prices
they'll accept higher prices
yeah basically where it finds the nearest liquidity
wherever the bid and ask is
it will start to place small limit orders
not market order longs but small limit orders in pieces
at wherever the bid and ask prices
so if we're looking at the bid and ask here
oh shit
because it's weekend
we can't see it
but this is the bid
this is the ask
they're the top of book
our prices
obviously this spreads
massive
because it's weekend
if you
trigger this algorithm
this execution algorithm
to go aggressive
fill 100 billion
within a 50 pip range
or within a 50 pip
limit distance
it will take
this buy
this 100 billion
you're trying to buy
they'll start
to place liquidity
at the price
very close to the bid.
Oh, okay.
Right?
So any selling that comes in,
it quickly finds the bid,
and your order,
which is trying to get filled
as quickly as possible,
you know,
it's there,
it's supporting prices very quickly.
Are you following me?
Yeah.
So again,
what that results in is,
price runs up,
the market order dries off,
your algorithm's unaggressive
trying to fill 100 billion,
so it quickly places orders here.
And then any selling that comes through
finds the buy liquidity,
you're trying to buy $100 billion.
It's a win-win, no?
And then, you know, so buy liquidity
follows price very, very closely.
If it moves up, it moves up with it.
Resulting in prices similar to this.
You can see, price moved down, sell equity moved down with it.
Price moved down, sell equity move down with it.
Price moves down, sell equity move down with it.
Price moves down, sell equity moves down with it.
resulting in thin pullbacks
pop
sorry stop pop
stop pop all right
so until until the whole order
gets filled
until the whole order gets filled
or it reaches the limit price
i.e you want to get filled in 50 pips
if it goes to 51 pips it cancels the rest of the order
so here we see and why price is super aggressive
here why is it not pulling back
why the inefficiencies not getting filled
is because whoever's filling in the large order
is accepted lower and lower prices on
automated basis through
through algorithms
which places the liquidity
at very very close to the bid and ask
now put it this way
prices run down the market order
selling is dried off sell liquidity turns up here
quickly it's very unlikely that
the move is basically that
there's weak sell liquidity here
because it's consistently following price
until it's all filled
so that's why the inefficiencies not getting filled
straight away. There's still more
selling to go on. In an
instance where this Algo
was put on passive
which means that they're okay
with price moving away from them
for a bit. So the Algo's on passive
so here's the bid and ask price
where do you think
this hundred billion will get placed in the book?
If aggressive is trying to get it filled
as quickly as possible willing to accept higher
and higher prices. You'll get the
the best prices.
An X percentage away from the
and ask. So this 100 billion might get placed a bit further away. You follow me? Yeah.
So now, if you look at this price move, for example, here you had buying going on, price popped out, ran away, market order buying dries off, the algorithm's on passive. So rather than accepting buy liquidity at higher prices, it keeps it down here. Are you following me?
much, much further away from the top of the book.
And just to give you an example,
you know,
you have to remember,
it's happening throughout this move as well.
So the further price travels,
the liquidity stays relatively further distance away from it.
Okay.
If it goes up,
it stays this distance.
Now,
price comes down,
finds the buy liquidity,
price moves out again.
Again,
the liquidity isn't following prices aggressively,
but it is following a bit.
Price comes down,
finds bid by liquidity,
price moves out again,
again the buy liquidity is kind of staying in this region
some of it might follow price like another trader or other traders
might follow price a bit more aggressively but within this whole move
we're not seeing aggressive bi-liquity we're seeing very consistent bi-liquity
as you can see with these green lines but it's not aggressive
except in higher and higher prices it's actually remaining back down
at that core areas the origin areas these moves out of
moral function of what?
Oh, the aggressive ones.
Yeah, why they're happening?
Why are the aggressive ones coming in?
No.
The buy liquidity is here.
Oh, I see what you're saying.
I see what you're saying.
Okay, so if it was, no, it can't be aggressive, yeah?
Because if it was aggressive, price would have continued higher, no?
All of the liquidity would have accepted higher and higher and higher and higher prices, pushing price out.
But what I'm saying is the market and,
environment here is in a passive state, buy liquidity is not accepting high prices that aggressively.
So if all the real buy liquidity is here, and it is a buying environment, yeah, then what's
causing price to extend out like this?
Oh, volume, market order.
Market order, market order volume, weakest liquidity, because it's a thicker buy environment.
And then that causes responses from market makers.
They want to avoid taking on short positions in these specific environments.
They avoid taking shorts.
Buyers chase, chase, chase, chase, chase, chase, the volume dries off.
But the real willingness to transact, the real liquidity is back down there.
So there's two very, very different things I'm pointing out here.
Volume isn't necessarily what the FX market is based on.
It's more to do with where the liquidity is.
Although volume is very significant,
it's a significant way that people transact
for the most part
larger transactions are done on a price-sensitive basis
rather than their time-sensitive basis
price-sensitive meaning
they want to trade at their desired prices
time-sensitive meaning
they don't give too fucks about where prices
they don't need to get in that moment in time
so you're saying there's more
FX is more of a passive market yeah
yeah okay
especially with a large trader's behavior
behave, especially the way the large trade is trade, they're more passive in nature.
But of course, you have different levels of aggressiveness.
It's not just aggressive 100.
You can have like 50% aggression.
You know, it's a stupid way of putting it, but it's the way it is.
There's nuances and there's different levels of intensity in the aggression.
So you can have relatively stable moves like this, which are composed of consistent buying,
but not that aggressive
you can have
mad mad mad
aggressive buying like this
which is ridiculous
but it doesn't ever last that long
it turns stable again
and you can have
very very very efficient
selling or buying as well
do you get it
very very very aggressive
residual
illiquity so after such a large move like that
based of the coronavirus events, there is no real willingness to sell or buy any of these areas
until the market can recover. So whenever you have high, high volume periods, where the volume
goes crazy, after that, the volume will always contract. Here, we had high, high cell volume,
no buy liquidity to match it with, hence why price dropped 2,000 pips, 1,800 pips. So there could be
50 trillion that wants to trade here
it's ridiculous figure but let's just call it that
but it doesn't mean there's 50 trillion sold
yeah sold here
do you get it so there's not 50 trillion sold in that one
specific place but the whole
move yeah there is
we had record high volumes in March
the highest ever that's ever been traded on multi-level platforms
happened in March
equity providers were loving it
it wasn't actually market
order-based as well. A lot of this selling happened because algorithms were just accepting
lower and lower prices. You can go on finance magnets, which is an institutional kind of news
website, going back to March articles, they've discussed it, where previously in aggressive
environments, there's more market order selling going on, time-sensitive selling.
And within this period, it was still algorithms being tasked with executing large sell orders,
but they just let the algorithms do their job.
Like I said, the algorithms, they place limit orders in the book based on the level of aggression.
That's being input into it.
Yeah, I would have thought that was a market order, is there?
There is market order selling going on.
But what I'm saying is if there was everybody market order selling, you wouldn't really have had these periods of stability.
Price would have done this.
Yeah, fair enough.
Yeah.
Like it did it.
But within this period, what actually happened is you had obviously market order selling because it's weak by liquidity.
and there's a high level of urgency
to get out of long pound positions
everybody wants to go along the US dollar
so the market order selling is happening
but that market order selling is drying off here
leaving behind that relative thinness
but sell liquidity is here
is holding price down
then the market order selling comes
because there's much, much thicker sell equity there
weak by liquidity
market order sell comes through
price runs down the market order sell
dries off it doesn't
continue selling you would think in an urgent environment nobody's thinking like rationally everybody's
trying to sell sell sell sell sell rapid yeah but no it wasn't the case we had definitely a lot of
selling going on market orders but not in an irrational way rather what was happening is it was selling off
in more of a controlled environment where the algorithms were placing limit orders in the book you get it
The algorithm may have been tasked with filling a very large order.
It might have been fill $100 billion on aggressive mode.
So as price sells off, the sell liquidity follows.
The volume dries off, cell liquidity continues being placed there.
Resulting in consistently fix sell liquidity wherever price went.
The buy liquidity, because of the event and the effect on the sentiment and the attitude of traders,
buy liquidity and willingness to buy was nonexistent.
Do you get it?
So there's a lack of buyers, basically strong sellers,
but the sellers are selling in limit orders, not market orders.
That's kind of what happened there.
Now, let me show you, before I let you go.
It'll be like 10 minutes.
A HSBC proprietary kind of sales pitch thing they have on their website,
on the solutions part of the website,
we're in the...
HBSBC.
Oh, shit, yeah.
So what we've discussed,
us today is, yeah. We already
know that volume shock can cause
liquidity providers to withdraw liquidity
and it creates price inefficiencies where price
runs out. Trade steadily, leaves weakness
behind. When the volume dries off,
it takes much less selling to push
price down. We know this.
What I'm discussing with you is what actually
happens in more
realistic terms in markets
where within these large moves
imagine it happened
for like three, four, five days of
buying, it's actually
composed of multiple
so pops,
drying,
pops, drying, pops, dry and pops, drying.
Do you get it?
Yeah.
It's not just buying, buy and buying
for that whole period of five days.
Yeah.
Now, within that period of five days,
there's buy liquidity there.
There's still weak sell liquidity here.
There's still weakness in sellers there.
Any market order buyer
that comes through pushes price out.
The market order buyer dries off
because volume is not a constant.
However, the liquidity consistently accepts
higher and higher prices for that period of buying.
As a result of, why is this kind of dynamic occurring?
Why are we seeing in buy liquidity except higher and higher prices?
Why are we in that environment in FX?
It's because large transactions have to be filtered in the market in small pieces.
You cannot just go market order short $10 trillion and get filled.
Nobody can do that.
There is not enough liquidity to do that.
You have to break your pieces, your large volume down at the small.
pieces like this $100 billion and this import into these algorithms which are a relatively new
thing and the algorithm handles the execution for you. It filters the liquidity in the market
and it filters you out of positions over time. So if you went to a firm like a large hedge fund
that needs to get filled for a large transaction, you don't just sit there and fill an order
in it. You will be taxed as Zane by your manager.
get this fucking order filled
by the end of today
I want this order filled
within this period
within this price
they won't say to you
fill a million at the ask price
it would be your job
as a trader
to oversee a trading decision
probably made by the manager
right
it's just your job to import it
into the market
you don't prick
you better make sure this is filled
within this price
go do it with this
dealer, go do it with on this
algorithm, we need to
get in by this point.
You get it. You don't sit there and make
trading decisions like, yeah, price is going to go
up, so I'm going to buy here, price. It's none
of that. This is only, that
type of trading only happens at
proprietary trading firms, which are
very, very small prop firm, basically.
You sit there, you rent a desk and you
try to trade and make money.
Right? They
are not institutional traders. You could even
class them as retail, to be honest.
Obviously, there's large prop firms and like Tom Dente used to work for one.
Navsing used to work for one.
But the world of prop trading, they never have been south side.
They've brought liquidity.
Hedge funds are very, very large buyers of liquidity.
They have huge liquidity issues.
So over the years, hedge funds, liquidity providers alike,
have invested in these execution suites, in a hotel suite,
into these execution suites which solve this issue.
They allow them to fill large trades over time in small pieces,
avoid adverse market volatility, avoid adverse selection,
basically avoid information leaking and then somebody responding to them.
It facilitates them hiding the information arising from the order flow
and essentially filling trades with the least volatility and lowest execution costs possible,
which is a very, very significant issue for large traders.
this is why as retail traders
we have a simple
it's more simplistic
in that sense
if you want to go buy
you buy and you get filled
if you want to sell you sell you sell
you get filled
there is none of that major issues
around having to fill
a large trade over the next two days
right so
and you know
as we discussed before
me and you don't move the market
so we are
chump's in this market
we are nobody knows
we exist basically
it is hedge fund
a hedge fund that's trying to short the pound
because they are taking money out
the UK economy for example
their volume can be significant
enough to move price
because they'll be dealing directly
to a liquidity provider
the liquidity provider's setting
bid and ask quotes
so here
there's thick sell liquidity
there's relative weakness in bi-liquity
a hedge fund has huge
sell limit orders there
now the dealer
can see that information right
Now, let's just say another client, a corporate client, goes market order short for a quick second.
The dealer responds to that market order short, sees that there's weak bids.
If he goes long, he can't get out of the long position.
So he withdraws his bids, causes price to chase his buy volume.
They pull that sell, sorry, buy liquidity, they pull that sell volume from the corporate client lower into the book, trying to find buyers sitting in the book.
meanwhile the hedge fund in this instance was super super aggressive he wanted to get filled
he's like fuck it i'll chase the price lower the algorithm chases the price lower and it holds
this wherever the price goes the sell liquidity goes with it resulting in quite consistently
thick sell liquidity throughout this whole move which is a very very mad thing you think about it
which person is willing to accept more expensive prices regardless yeah someone who's trying to get
bit of it quick.
Yeah.
Event driven.
Anyway,
let me pull up
this thing
so you don't
think I'm trying
shit to you
basically.
How does this guy
know how large
how the fuck
do I know
how banks
what kind of
options they
offer to their clients
so HSPC
liquidity algorithm
it's a floating
iceberg order
but already
what that means
is iceberg is
so think about it
you have the sea
you have the tip
of the iceberg
and then the iceberg
underneath the sea
could be like that big
the tip of the iceberg you can't actually see how big the real iceberg is
now if i have a hundred billion order and i use an iceberg order
what they always do is you might want to transact a hundred billion
but it will only show one million at a time
okay so anybody who ever sees what's sitting in the order book
just see the tip of the iceberg they can only see the tip of the iceberg yeah
but obviously there's ways to tell that it's an iceberg order
if this is the same level and one million keeps turning up without
ever going away no matter how much you could buy 500 million but it just isn't going anywhere
it's because there's a fucking large order there you get it anyway you can start the sort of end
time you can limit price so how you know what price you want to get filled within if I want to
fill a hundred million but I needed to fill with to get filled within 100 pips my hundred pips
in my limit price you have the liquidity pool you can execute internally with HSBC's internal liquidity
pool or you can execute externally with the actual market, probably on EBS.
Now, what they say is, you can balance the trade-off between execution and information leakage.
So if you trade inside of HSBC, there's less information leakage and less likelihood of price
of other people basically becoming and taking advantage of basically of your information.
If it becomes quite obvious that there's a large, large buyer and everybody knows that
information. Everybody that buys ahead of you, causing price to move away and it becomes more expensive
to fill your order. Now, if you want to hide that information from the market and you want to fill it
in-house with HSPC, it might take like fucking six days to fill it. Yeah. Or HSPC, you might tell HSPC to
fill you 100 billion within 100 pips. You don't want information leakage, so you want them to fill it in-house.
They will not be able to fill you 100 pips within 100 pips. They might only get.
done, 70 million.
Do you get it?
So you can balance it.
Oh yeah, it shows you on the right as well.
Aggressive, neutral and passive.
Yeah.
So aggressive means
percent of total order size done
between this much time,
done between this much time
and then the passive one done within this much time.
But just because
this is executing quicker for you,
it tells you here
the algorithm will place orders
inside the spread. That's
my bro. So price is here right now. Yeah. It places by limit orders here. If it's a,
if it's a, that's, that's the, that's very tight. Yeah. So think about it. It results in,
wherever the price goes, it results in thick by liquidity. Think about it. Thick by liquidity.
Consistently is present and any market orders that come through, which way, which, you know,
is likely the sell side is going to be weaker. So when price pushes up, the bid and ask is
now here, the algorithm continues to place the liquidity within the spread.
That's mad. That's actually mad.
Neutral, the algorithm will be moderately risk-averse
and place child, basically, baby orders, close to the top of work.
So here's the bid and ask spread. It'll place them here.
So when price has popped out and has become inefficient and dried off,
if it's on neutral, the liquidity will get placed around here, close to the top of work.
Leaving that weakness in the middle, market orders dry off,
price draws back down, finds the liquidity, pops again, and the liquidity might accept here now.
Resulting in the stair-step type, quite relatively efficient structure.
The aggressive execution, whether it's placed inside the spread, will result in a much more thinner and efficient price move.
Because consistently, the bi-liquity is here now.
It's moved up from here, here, here, here.
any market order
sell that comes through
finds buyers quickly
the sell liquidity
relatively remains weaker
any market order by that comes
through continues to push price up
you follow him
and then passive
it places smaller orders
deeper in the book
so here's the origin
price pops out
remains down here
price comes all the way down
so as you can imagine
depending on how orders are being filled
it can result in very very thin
inefficient moves
more stable moves
or it can result in really
really stable environment
Yeah, you backed that up pretty well
I'll give you that
Yeah, anyway, I'll leave it at that
I'll send this algorithm if you want
You can probably find the links here
On that other website
The point of the topic today has been
How yes, market makers and liquidity providers
They do create inefficiencies
And they do cause price they over-extend
But within the real market
It's not just that granular, it's not that black and white
There's extra details and information present
Larger trade is the way they transact
the way they fill orders causes liquidity to chase price sometimes depending on the level of
aggression of the algorithm but one of the main main takeaways is that liquidity if price runs higher
you're you're going to one day ask me why did it not fill back down here it's because the
liquidity is accepting higher prices there okay would you see that in price yes there'd be areas
there'd be areas where we expect
buy liquidity to stay there
and there'd be times where we expect
that buy liquidity here to be weak
and price it could finally reverse
okay well as long as you can see it
yeah but that kind of explains then
why you have long term moves
that result in this
so you go oh that inefficiency there didn't get filled
and why did well the fucker
it's because there's a lot of buying going on
until that buying dries off
which you will be able to see
you won't get that large fill yet
yeah sometimes you can just fall straight past it as well yeah um so that's that the environment then
can be explained based of how transactions form there's if there's buy liquidity here it's impossible
that price would sell off until sellers absorb it or the buyers withdraw if there's weakness on
one side of the book it's weak sell liquidity here thicker buy liquidity here market order sales will
get filled any market order buy the liquidity providers will trigger the response then with
the draw price will pop out the liquidity can stay back at the core when that move dries off price
will have to come back down to the origin in a more realistic scenario if there's a hundred
million here 10 million might follow it so 10 million liquidity accepts higher and higher prices
holds price up once that 10 million's finished there's still majority of the liquidity is back down
at the origin is still traded thinly on the way up price ends up filling it anyway so it's not ever
just a singular cause there's buy limits chasing price higher there's market order buyers pushing
the price higher the majority the buy limits can remain down there it's just completely no
sell liquidity here there is sell liquidity there in realistic scenarios okay but broadly speaking much
thicker much thinner price goes to the thinner side anyway i leave it at that